Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the macroverse.
Today we're going to continue our
collaboration series. This time with
Jason Pazino. I'm honored to have Jason.
Uh we've done some collaborations with
Jason before. I was on his channel a few
months ago. If you don't know where to
find Jason, I'm going to leave a link
down to his YouTube channel in the
description below. And he also has a
website, ta tiainvestor.com.
Is that right, Jason?
>> Got it right. Yeah.
>> Well, Jason, it's it's great to have you
back here. How's it going?
>> Excellent, mate. Very very glad to be
back as well.
>> Yeah. So, what I what I thought we could
talk about, I mean, obviously people
want to talk about uh Bitcoin. I mean,
there's, you know, been some pretty
exciting moves over over there recently,
but in order to understand that, I know
you're a big believer in the real estate
cycle, right? And and I've I've seen you
talk about it a lot, and to be
completely honest, I mean, like, I sort
of loosely follow it. Like, I'm not a
real estate investor. I'm not and I know
real estate is also somewhat localized.
I guess it's not the same everywhere,
but I'd be really interested to hear
your take on the real estate cycle and
how that could influence other markets,
you know, over over the next few years.
So, I want to just give you the floor to
kind of share share what you think's
going on over over in real estate and
then maybe we can take that to get an
idea of what might happen over in in
other markets.
>> Yeah, I reckon that's a a good idea. And
if you got any ideas that come up while
we're chatting about it, obviously drop
it. You know, we'll have the discussion
about it too because I'm sure other
people that are listening are obviously
interested in the US market, other
markets. Um, and then some people just
blatantly don't have an in or look at a
real estate cycle at all. So, let's see
if we can bring a few of these ideas
together and and see what sticks.
>> Absolutely. I mean, I real estate is is
sort of it's the one one part of one
asset class that I I don't really feel
like I have the best handle on.
>> Well, I I'll start with the broad
outlook on the cycle and then we'll sort
of dig down into it. So, I'll just share
one of my screens here that has
this chart that I share quite often.
Looking at that 18ear cycle, I've got a
little yellow dot at the top. That's
roughly where we we sit.
This is the top. Basically, this is
broken down into three sections. First
half, second half and the peak collapse.
Now, all of this stuff, the data was
collected from about 220 years of US
real estate sales data going back to
1800. That was put together by um
property share market economics. So,
Phil Anderson and he's also got a guy
here, a kill. So a basic I I'll start
with the cycle itself. The the cycle
that we're currently in started around
2011 2012. So it's the US real estate
and economic cycle. Now of course I'm
I'm not American. I don't have an
American accent, but I focus on the US
real estate cycle because that's the
biggest market in the world where most
of the money is. And basically, it all
trickles out from that point, which will
then affect the markets that I'm
investing in in in Australia. And you
know, I've looked at Southeast Asia and
those other places for real estate
investing. Now, it's also real estate
and economic cycle because this is what
obviously like a credit cycle where
where the money is flowing to. Now, the
first half of the cycle is usually when
people don't believe that the the cycle
has begun. And I don't know if you
remember back to like 2011 through to
20134, it was tons of fear, tons of
recession calls. We had fears of
>> Europe collapsing, uh, Greece going into
debt with Germany and Greece was going
to lose its place in the euro and all
this sort of stuff. So, the first half
of the cycle, no one believes that we've
begun a new cycle. We get to the peak of
it and then basically everyone starts to
believe that we're there. Around 2018
through to 20 early 2020 was the last
peak of before the midcycle slowdown
that happened in 2020. We had the
catalyst was the the co event. So we
don't know what the events are going to
be leading into these periods but we
just know that the cycle leads us into
these areas.
From there we start the next cycle or
the the next half of the cycle. So 2020
through to roughly 2022 we had the money
printing, we had the pullback and then
things start to get going 23 24
where the last two years of this second
half are what they call like a winner's
curse. Basically everyone's been making
money over these last few years.
Everyone wants to make more money.
Everyone's sort of getting leveraged up
into their positions. And it's kind of
what we're seeing now with the major
IPOs, huge construction projects going
on, lots of money being invested into
all sorts of things, which leads us into
this peak. Basically, everyone's got to
be in the market like what we know about
Bitcoin. Once everyone's in, you're at
the peak. So, we're kind of getting to
that that point now for the stock
market. Whereas for real estate, uh that
usually happens first and then things
start to eventually roll over. It's not
like a singular event, although that's
the way we often remember it in history,
like the, you know, the catalyst of 2008
with Lehman Brothers collapsing. That's
the sort of thing everyone remembers it
for, but things were slowing down from
2006, which then led us to the lows of
2009 for the stock market and 20112 for
real estate and the economy. So, that's
kind of the the overlay of of the cycle.
roughly 14 years up, two events, you got
something that breaks it in the middle
almost every single time and then
we have the the collapse at the end of
the cycle, the mid cycle. Go on.
>> I I said I I was just want to say I
remember you talking about this back in
probably what 2021. I mean, you probably
talked about it before then, frankly,
but I remember you talked about it back
then, and I like I honestly wasn't even
necessarily on the same page as you.
Like, I I was somewhat doubtful, I
think, at the time that like real estate
could continue to just go higher for the
next like several, but you're right.
Right. Like, I mean, it has. And like I
it's been amazing to see, you know, real
estate prices just go up basically up
only in so I mean there's been some
places where it's gone down but for the
most part real estate has done
exceptionally well uh for for a long
time. Is it when you say like 2025 2026
like are you do you already see signs
that it's breaking down or are we still
waiting for for those signs? like where
where do you think exact like where in
the process would you say we are
>> for the US real estate we're basically
where this yellow dot is at the top so
this is like a national average
for the pricing
>> in some areas which obviously you know
the US is massive
>> and there's markets within markets you
see some of the markets that have been
correcting since about 2022
>> uh and some of them are are getting
going again that have basically been
declining for years. I think San
Francisco was one of those and there's a
couple of those areas around like the
the West Coast that were just everyone
wrote them off and now they're starting
to bounce back a bit. So, broadly
speaking for these peaks, we're
somewhere around this top now.
>> Okay. But I one thing I've always wanted
to ask you with this because I I think a
lot of people when they think about this
cycle, right? It's it's natural to think
back to the last one and and that was
2008. And in 2008, I mean the whole
housing market was basically collapsing.
I mean like prices were dropping what 30
40% some places maybe even more. Um,
does that like when you go back every 18
years, is it it's not always like that,
right? I mean, like you get drops like
that. So,
>> what are the odds? Like, do you think
it's more likely to be like that or
could it be somewhat a muted version of
that maybe like it was in the 1980s or
the 18 years before that? Like, what are
you thinking this one's going to be?
>> Well, the it's obviously no one knows.
We we always say that but we're looking
for a slowdown at least and
>> there was some some data that I saw a
little while back that said
>> every 40 years. So you had the the big
collapse in 2008. The one before that
for the US was around two 1989 to 1992
for this low and it wasn't as severe and
then the one before that was a little
more severe. So this time round it might
not be as severe for the US and you're
kind of seeing that with the data from
uh the homebuilders. Some of the home
builders are holding up a little better
than they were last cycle because they
were all leveraging up and basically
uh you know just taking things far too
far at the peaks of the cycle. Whereas
this time they don't hold as much I
believe it's they don't hold as much
land. So they're not really in that
position where they'll get hit when
things do turn down. So, you're not
seeing it as severe as what we did last
time. In Australia, we might be on the
opposite uh cycles for this because
we've just gone absolutely nuts in
Australia. Property prices, everyone did
not believe that that real estate prices
would come down in Australia. If you
spoke to them last year, come May this
year, we had our budget and all these
things changed and it's just like a
light flipped and things are down 5 10%
in some areas. Top end is down 20 25%
here. Well, didn't Australia haven't
they been raising interest rates over
the last like couple of quarters?
>> Yeah, we've been raising I think since
February or March. So, we're at 4.35.
Last year they dropped it three times
and they've increased it three times
back to that same level possibly with
another increase coming before the the
peak. Just inflation's been still high
here.
>> So, you think there could be are you
saying there could be a larger drop
potentially in Australia in the real
estate market than in the United States?
>> Than the United States this time around.
Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Yeah, because I was
thinking I was thinking back to the 19
the the one you have labeled here that
ended in ' 89, I guess, because the
stock market, the S&P had a correction
in 1990 that was probably on the back of
the top end real estate market, but it
was only a 20% drop in in the stock
market, which isn't that bad compared to
like the 50 to 60% drop that we got in
2000 and 2008. Um so it is you know I
think it's each each each of these big
draw downs or periods of in the real
estate or a recession in real estate can
have very different effects I I suppose
on on the stock market um would you
would you
>> in the late 80s we also had the black
Monday so I think that that fell 40 or
was it 35 to 50%
>> in 1987
>> yeah yeah so it was a huge draw down and
then the next one I think you a lot of
the sellers had gotten out at that
point. So, we still
>> That's a great point. That's a good
point.
>> You know, it happens all the time. It's
like you Yeah. big pullbacks and then
it's not as severe the next time around.
So, the main thing with that though is
with the peak of the real estate cycle
is real estate typically peaks first.
Every time you go back through these
roughly 18 years, you get real estate
peaking, then you'll get stock markets.
Uh metals usually come after that. And I
think you've also pointed out that
energy comes through that which is the
commodities. So you start to see
commodities peak. It doesn't mean that
they all run to all-time highs at the
end of these cycles, but they start to
have a little uptick. Like 1989, 1990,
gold was off the back of a huge spike in
1980. So it wasn't going to run to a new
all-time high at the end of that
economic cycle, but it still held out
and then died off into the 90s to that
low in 2001. So,
>> so for for people that are like I
imagine there's a lot of people that
watch your channel, that watch my
channel, but are maybe our age, maybe a
little bit younger, and they're looking
to to buy a house uh at some point, but
a lot of them feel like they've been
completely priced out. If if this is
true, right? Like so if this 18-year
cycle plays out,
when would you expect the trough or, you
know, the the valley to occur in in
prices, whatever they are, whether it's
like, you know, 10% down, 20%, whatever
it is, when would you expect those
opportunities to to be most likely to
occur?
>> All right. So, like you said, cycles
within cycles and you've got different
areas, but if we're just talking
national averages,
>> right?
>> What we've seen is about four years from
the peak.
>> Okay.
>> So, it could be 2029, 2030.
>> This is for the US national average,
>> right?
>> Yeah.
>> Right. I mean, I guess it depends on
when exactly the peak is, but you're
saying we're really close to the peak
now
>> for the real estate. Yeah, we're pretty
close now. I'll just show a couple of
other things and I'll come back to this
this chart here. So
I'll just share like a screen.
So this is
Dr. Horton
DHI. So I think this is the biggest
uh where am I? Yeah, this one. Biggest
home builder in the US.
And with the prior cycles, you start to
get a bit of a lead on it. I know not
not many people use the homebuilders as
basically their their signal for the
stock market peaking, which is fair
enough. They're not the biggest
companies, but we look back at each of
the price cycles. We have a d we've got
data here for the last two. Um Dr.
Horton at the peak hit around uh peaked
in 2005, lower high in 2006, lower high
2007 and by the time the stock market
had peaked, it was like I think 60 to
70% down from its high. Stock market
peaked in September, October. There it
is, 70% down. So, it was giving a bit of
a a lead that things weren't stable in
the real estate market uh long before
the stock market peaked. and then it
bottomed before the stock market
bottomed. So, you start to get that
earlier lead that things are recovering.
Doesn't mean it's going to take off to
new fresh highs and outperform the stock
the stock market because you can see
here the S&P we know bottomed in March
2009, but it's giving a lead that things
aren't as bad. Um, you know, I was how
old was I there? 23 24 years old and it
was just it was horrendous. It's like if
people are young watching this now, you
just have no idea what the pain that
everyone was going through through 2009,
10, 11, 12, 13 for 4, 5 years from that
point. But the market's showing you that
it's probably not as bad as what the
news is making out. And they're the
opportunities to be getting in. So
that's like the massive blood on the
street. You had the 18ear cycle low. So
there's a higher low here for Dr. Horton
telling us that the conditions are
improving. And then you can see it's
just basically off to the races for that
first half of the cycle. Started to slow
down around 2018, 2019,
January 2020. Okay, spare us a month
correction and then we're off to the
races for the second half of the cycle.
And now we've got a peak late 2024.
Last cycle was about 27 months until the
stock market peaked. So I'm watching out
sometime around uh the first half of
2027 to see if this happens again for a
stock market peak. And in the cycle
before that, we don't have the data for
DHI, but you can see the cycle lower
occurred in 1992
and that was the bottom of the last
cycle, ran up into the midcycle peak,
corrected into the midcycle, and then
ran up again for the second half of the
cycle.
>> So, do you think do you think there's
any chance this thing could hit new
highs or do you think it's kind of
already in that correction phase right
now?
>> Like DHI,
>> right? Do you think the home builders is
there any is it like is there a chance
is there is there time if the if the
high doesn't occur till say like 2025 20
is it possible that it could it could go
back up uh briefly or or does it seem
more likely that it's kind of already in
that phase of looking trying to like
carve out future lows
I would be more confident once it breaks
the lows so once DHI broke like 130 then
it's probably going to come back and
test the low and the halfway point at
50% event, but you you know you know as
well as I that these patterns suck to
try and guess anything in
>> I mean we even see that pattern with
Bitcoin right now to some degree. I mean
you're seeing lower highs and and you
know some higher lows and so that kind
of brings me my my next question is if
if this is all true, right? If if the
real estate market is in this 18ear
cycle and let's suppose that that um you
know we're kind of near the highs give
or take, right? like it's hard to know
exactly the the month, but give or take
if we're near the highs. And let's say
you're right and the real estate cycle,
you know, starts to roll over, the real
estate market starts to roll over and
and we form a trough out in 2019, 2029,
2030. H how do you think that would
affect the the crypto markets? Um
because I mean, Bitcoin has arguably
been in a bare market. I know not
everyone agrees with this, but Bitcoin
has been in a bare market by most
metrics, I think you would say, since
October of last year. Um,
>> sure.
>> So, I mean, more people right now seem
to be more looking for lows in Bitcoin,
not, you know, not for this thing. So,
do do you think that like how do you
think this will affect the crypto cycle?
Like, could it affect how Bitcoin's
cycles normally play out? Could it could
it temper Bitcoin's future returns if if
this were to play out? I mean, I'm just
curious what your thoughts are on it
because I mean, right now, everyone's so
focused on just getting through the
midterm year, it can often be hard to
think about, you know, what happens in
2027 or what happens in 2028.
>> I I think there is still a good chance
Bitcoin rallies from here. Whether the
low is July, whether the low's October,
who knows? But I think there's a good
chance that Bitcoin will still rally.
whether it's going to be the same sort
of rally that we're used to from, you
know, the last bull market 2022 to 2025,
you know, the bull market before that,
the bull market before that where we had
these huge multi- hundreds of a percent
gains. I think it's more unlikely that
we would see something like this again.
We obviously know the diminishing
returns that that you've coined. We've
got the um every cycle there's less and
less gains. This might be one of those
cycles where we just don't see huge move
from these lows. Say, say 57k is a low.
100% takes us to about 120. So barely a
new alltime high. If that 200% takes us
to 180, it's hard to see it happening if
everything else is is turning down.
Credit's contracting, the economy is not
as strong as what we've been told and
and what the data is coming out as, and
the stock market eventually turns down
in a year or two. So yeah, it's not to
say we can't get a rally and that would
be, you know, a significant rally as
well.
>> So you think there could be some time
between, you know, a potential cycle low
in the midterm year and then when the
the real estate market or potential
deterioration in the real estate market
might actually start to temper Bitcoin's
returns.
>> Yes. Yes. So with the as we said with
the real estate cycle here we are here
the
real estate usually tops first and the
stock market can keep running and it and
almost every cycle the stock market has
run beyond the real estate cycle
topping. So stock market topped 2007 you
know I've got the Dow Jones just because
there's the most data here. It topped in
2007 real estate topped 2006. Dow Jones
topped in mid 1990. Real estate topped
around 1989.
In the 70s, the stock market topped in
73. I think it was around 72 where real
estate topped. Had a quick one down and
then came back for that first half. Uh
1929 was a was a crazy one. Real estate
topped around 1926
and the stock market ripped until 1929.
So it doesn't mean that just because the
real estate is peaking that it's all
over. We're just much closer to the end
than the beginning as one indicator.
>> Yeah. I mean it's interesting that it
gives us such a such a lead time like I
mean even a multi-year lead time it it
seems that it gives us. Um
>> yeah the best like the longest ones have
been multi-year. There's been obviously
some short ones like 2005 six into the
peak of 2007. So yeah, about a year, 18
months or so. Um,
yeah, that's that's kind of where we're
looking at it when it comes to the tops.
One one thing I forgot to mention was
the midcycle. How to identify those
midcles because through that that period
of 2020 and then into 2022 where we had
the Silicon Valley bank collapsing. If
you remember early 23, we had the bare
market in 22 with inflation fears and in
2020 it was uh obviously the the
pandemic and everything was just
everything tanked. The midcycles are
typically non landled recessions. So
it's something else that needs to have a
correction whether it's the banking
sector, something financial. Uh yeah,
typically something financial like look
2000 was the tech the tech boom. So
there was a ton of money going into the
space. It was all a big bubble that had
to clear out of the system before we had
that next leg up for real estate. So
midcycles are usually finance related
rather than the land prices coming down
substantially.
>> I see. Okay.
>> A big difference. Yeah. 1980 remember
the US was going to default to Mexico or
something like that. 1980 1981 we had
the recession into 82 and then things
took off again.
>> Yeah. I mean and I think too the thing
about the business cycle is and I think
about this a lot. I mean, if if you
exclude the pandemic, the last time we
even had a recession around the time of
a real estate collapse was what in in
2008. And I mean, I was still in high
school at the time. Like, I I think I I
think a lot of a a lot of people, you
know, my age just haven't even seen all
that stuff happen, right? Like, we just
don't even it's just been up only
forever. Um I mean, and and it's hard
like it's hard not to get sucked into
that, right? Right. I mean, like I' I'd
just buy index funds every single month.
I mean, it's hard it's kind of hard not
to, right? Because they just keep going
up and up and up and up. Um, but yeah, I
mean, I I guess at some point, right,
and we shouldn't we shouldn't be of the
opinion that we'll never have to
experience hard times. Um, I mean, even
some of the best investors in the world,
right, are like, you will experience,
you know, some really large draw downs
throughout your investing career. And,
you know, you just have to live with
that, right? You have to live with that
and and and be okay with it. And I think
that's something that I, you know, I had
to learn to be okay with long ago. Um,
but it is, I mean, it seems like
something like that is going to happen
probably within the next few years,
right? Like there's going to be some
type of change in the business cycle,
changing of the guard and and something
new happens, right?
>> I think your the business cycle that you
put together, what do you call it?
>> Um, you have
>> I think I just call it the business
cycles. Yeah, business cycles, I think.
I don't think I even called it anything.
[laughter]
>> It needs a name because it it lines up
very well with the 18year cycle. You
show like the midcycle slowdowns. You
show the end of cycles
>> and it all lines up really really well.
>> The thing about it though is that that
chart though isn't the best for telling
you ex I mean it helps you visualize it
all, right? like it helps you see where
the cycles are are kind of ending at,
but it doesn't tell you exactly when the
top's going to be. But I I mean, I guess
no chart really does that, right? No
chart's going to tell you the exact
month or year the the top has to be, but
I I think it's just a great way to to
visualize um to help people visualize
how these things can can take years to
play out, right? And and in in crypto, I
mean, a lot of people are more so
interested in like what's going to
happen tomorrow um rather than like what
might happen over the next like say five
years. And it requires a lot more
patience, I think, when you're talking
about more macro things.
>> Yeah. And that's probably something
you've noticed over the years. Many
people don't have patience. So
hopefully, you know, if people can bring
that patience together for their
investing, then you're able to go to
those next steps and last
>> throughout the ups and the downs.
Speaking of patience, the next the next
cycle may not just be a correction like
2008, bottoms 2009, and then takes off
>> for 17 years.
>> We could go through that sort of up and
down, and it's just trying to everything
catch up to the elevated prices that
we're currently at. So, you know, have
you looked at those things where it's,
you know, this lost decade coming up or
a lost 15 years where it's just turning
around like the 70s? I'm sure that's
been thrown out a lot of times.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean, I I probably will
happen at some point. It's just hard to
know what year it starts, right? And,
you know, in in the 90s, you look at
like the mid 90s when they like the the
Fed raised rates and then they lowered
rates and then they raised them again 25
basis points. the stock market had a
correction and and you know there's talk
about the Fed raising rates again. Um
but you know if if you had panic sold
when the Fed raised rates in 97 I think
it was 9796 or something like that. I
think it was 97. You know by the time
the recession actually arrived and you
had a lost decade the low of the
recession was actually higher than where
the stock market was when people
panicked with that rate hike. So that
that's why it's so hard is like yes we
probably will have a lost decade at some
point but it's like at what level does
that occur from right does it occur from
you know from these prices or does it
occur from like you know 40% higher 30%
higher and I think that's really hard to
>> you know to to get down what are your
thoughts on on the Fed here because I
mean there's a lot of really polarizing
views right now I mean on one hand
there's you know there's some residual
inflation issues that we've seen uh with
energy prices and whatnot But on the
other hand, we get these non-farm
payroll reports and we're losing jobs,
but the unemployment rate's going down
at the same time. So, I mean, it's kind
of a confusing
time for for the macro because, you
know, in in some parts of the labor
market, it seems like things are okay,
then other parts seem like they're not
necessarily that great. Um, and then I
think even Trump, uh, I I mean, it's
hard to even know what to believe
anymore when I see it on on X or on
Twitter cuz like I mean, who knows if
it's just AI, but I I saw something
where he said, you know, that you you
know, raising rates is a sign of a
strong a strong economy, right? And like
he's right, right? Like it is, but
that's definitely a different thing than
he was saying six months ago when he was
like yelling at Powell to cut rates. Uh,
so do you think he's like preparing
people for a rate hike? Do you think
we're gonna have a rate hike over here?
I mean, you guys have already been
dealing with rate hikes in Australia and
also New Zealand. New Zealand had a rate
hike, I believe. Uh, the Euro area had a
rate hike. Japan has been raising rates.
Yeah. I mean, a lot of places have been
raising rates. Are is the US gonna
follow or what do you think?
I mean, you know, you you and I both
know it's like we're just spitting
here, but
>> we're we're armchair economists.
[laughter]
>> Yeah, exactly. We probably don't do any
any worse than actual economists, but um
you know,
>> I think eventually they'll have to
whether it's the next thing they do.
It's I don't know. But I think before
the the end of the cycle, so whether
it's the real estate cycle and then into
the stock market cycle, I think they'll
have to raise at least once. It's just
to to cool things off.
>> That's typically what happens. We saw it
in 2007,
saw it in leading up into 2000, you saw
it leading into the 1980s. So it's just
one of those things that typically
happens towards the end because well,
everything's just getting out of hand.
Too many things are going up. the animal
spirits are are reigning basically.
>> Yeah.
>> And then they always act late, which you
you know, you've already covered with
the two-year and the 10-year that have
already started raising. You know,
they've the bonds the yields have been
going up and the Fed's not doing
anything. And I think they're trying to
do everything they can to hold the rates
where they are.
>> Yeah. Well, came out came out today. I
mean, they're clearly trying to to keep
the the long end down. I mean, that's
what they want to do. We'll see if
there's I mean, the dollar sold off a
lot today. And I like I I mean just for
the reference, we're we're recording
this video on August 19th. So I mean
this will probably be out on my channel
within a couple of days or a few days.
Uh but when they you know I I've been
bullish on the dollar um this year. And
I mean it is still up this year
technically speaking, but it's not up as
much as I probably thought it was going
to be. Like it's been you know it's
every time it goes up and puts in a
higher high then like goes right back
down and and then prints sort of like a
higher low. And it's just it it's it
feels somewhat like they they want the
dollar to go down this year, but it
still is kind of fighting back and not
really allowing it. It is not really
fully going down like the way they want
it to. Um but anyways, what are there
anything else anything else you'd like
to add to this? I mean, I And by the
way, guys, if if you're not familiar
with uh Jason, um he will be speaking at
the ITC conference, the Investing
Through the Cycle Conference in Miami in
November. Uh so, if you're curious about
this stuff, you want to learn more about
real estate and how maybe that can
affect other assets that you care about
like Bitcoin, make sure you guys uh come
to the conference and and come hear
Jason speak. But Jason, is there
anything you'd like to, you know, kind
of leave it off on for for people here
who are wondering how to navigate this
over the next few years?
>> Um, speaking of the US dollar, I'll add
to that with the the real estate cycle
and then, you know, we can get into uh
discussion on what to do with it really
because
>> right
>> without action, what the hell's the
point of things? Um the US dollar in the
first half of the real estate cycle
typically goes up and then in the second
half of the real estate cycle it
generally goes down.
>> I'll um
share a chart again.
Here we are.
>> I mean it's been going down since what
>> two. Yeah.
>> So what we got monthly here? I'll get
this chart. It's got more data.
bottom of the real estate cycle. There
it is. 2011, higher lows. You got the
low here in 2008 as well, but higher
lows. Ran ran up 2022 and it's been
coming down. So, it's not to say that
you, you know, your view is wrong that
it's not going to
>> Are you showing the are you showing the
dollar on your screen? I'm seeing Dow
Jones.
>> Here we go. Sorry. Uh US dollar
has been heading up from the lows,
>> right? pulling back and then yeah, your
view is that it's still going high, but
I think you were talking about like a
lower high. I
>> I think it's going up to a lower high
and then it's going to come back down
basically
>> like
104 105 area and then and then and then
kind of come back down as we get out
into the pre-election year and the
election year.
>> That that was my view at least. If even
if it gets to 105, yeah, lower high,
like you said, halfway point of the
entire range and then keeps coming down
to test these lows at 96. I think if it
gets past 97, which are these lows, 97
and a half, then it's probably unlikely
going to go any higher than than this
current peak at 1016.
So
>> yeah. Yeah, I mean I could I could see
that.
>> And that's the dollar now. Like we're
basically fighting over scraps here with
this range since midlast year. So
each of these times we're just expecting
it to do what it does every other cycle.
First half up, second half down,
consolidate for the the beginning of the
new cycle up, second half down,
consolidate for the next part of the
cycle, and then start it start its way
higher. If this happens to be a higher
low, that could be that could be a new
start for the US dollar heading higher,
which would be a massive contrarian idea
with the the general population thinking
that US dollar is over. You know, the
whole thing of the US dollar's finished,
it's going to China or some other bricks
currency or whatever's going on. I mean,
if this doesn't break the low, it's
basically been in a a massive trading
range now since the 1990s with this one
spike out of it in the 80s. So,
>> I mean, ever ever since I've been an
investor,
which is basically since I, you know,
was 18, 19 years old. Um, so this is
back in 2008, the dollar has generally
trended higher, right? But also,
arguably, we've been in the same
business cycle for the last
18 years, right? If you ignore the
pandemic, if you ignore that, which
plenty of reasons to ignore because it
was just such a quick thing kind of in
and out,
>> the dollar, I mean, I've just seen it go
higher. And um yeah, I mean, it'd be
interesting to see if if if that does
change. I mean, I know there's a lot a
lot of people are calling for the dollar
the dollar to go um low. There's some
investment banks recently. There's like
three different investment banks I was
reading about. They're all calling for
the dollar to go lower. though as well.
I just think I I I think that there
might be a reason to see it get one last
push before that larger drop occurs, but
I, you know, maybe I'm wrong about that.
I It's one of those things like strong
opinion, loosely held type thing.
>> Yeah. [laughter] Yeah. It's not really
going to make too much of a difference
here or there. If it's going down, then
the assets are going up. So, you know,
we saw gold pop off, silver pop off.
That's similar towards the end of the
real estate cycle where you're getting
commodities heading higher. I think
oil's still hanging out where it is.
>> Yeah. What are your thoughts on gold? I
mean, I've been really bullish on gold
for a while and I I think it's going to
go up. I mean, I feels like this is more
or less a reset year, but do you think
the highs for gold are already in? Like,
do you think there's a chance that it
that's already because I know there's a
lot of people that think that is the top
for gold right there? Like that is the
macro top.
>> Um, from your understanding of the
business cycle,
>> do you think it can still stay elevated
for a while? um especially considering
where the stock market is.
>> Definitely like there's no signs that
this is definitely the high yet. Silver
I'm a little bit unsure of but gold it
hasn't broken any of the key levels.
I've been talking about this just being
a like a dead cat bounce in this um
downtrend where it just needs to
consolidate for this year and I think
we'll get an answer in 2027. Each of
these prior moves, these have all been
roughly 16 to 19 months. So looking at
2020 2006 2008 2011 you see an answer in
about 16 to 19 months the top comes in a
breakout occurs whether it's breakout or
breakdown like in 20 I think it was 2012
or 2013. So if I'm measuring from this
peak roughly 16 to 19 months that takes
us to the first half of 2027
>> I think we'll get an answer whether it
is a breakout breakdown. The next thing
on that was if it holds above the
halfway point, then it's going to be a
break out to the upside. If it fails at
the halfway, it's probably going to come
down. This one here failed
at the top
one month above and closed underneath.
So, it just couldn't do two months above
and then eventually it broke down.
Whereas these ones here, they eventually
held above their halfway point. So, like
the 50% of the fib, you get a monthly
close and it's holding and then
eventually breaks out. Same thing
happened back here in 200 um six and
then again even in the 1980s it just
couldn't hold its 50% and then collapsed
came up and then eventually collapsed
and that also collapsed in about I think
it was 17 months. So really like a year
and a half at a 50% level should give us
the answer in 2027.
>> Yeah. And I think uh
I think it was in like the 70s when uh
gold had a pretty big drop. Silver also
had a massive drop. Then gold a lot of I
mean a lot of these business cycles gold
recovers to new highs before silver
does. It's almost like gold kind of
leads the way in a sense. Like if if
silver's going to go to new highs, you
would I would expect gold to need to go
to new highs first. Kind of like how
Bitcoin normally goes to new highs
before most altcoins go to new highs,
right? Like it kind of leads the way.
Well, I mean, silver went up
[clears throat]
>> I mean, silver went up massively uh last
year and and really going into the
beginning of this year. I mean, it had
actually outperformed gold by a ton. So,
um so you're less sure about silver.
>> Less sure at this point. Yeah. It's just
come off so much. I mean, it did it in
2008,
>> but that you still had so many signals
or so many so much time to get back in.
Yeah. you're not buying the low, but I
know you and I aren't interested in the
low, but there's still more signs it's
going to consolidate and then you get
these nice fast moves, the the exciting
stuff that everyone wants to trade for.
So,
>> I'm I'm happy to be patient on on
silver. I don't care if I don't get 55
bucks, 65, $66. If it gets above 88 and
consolidates, then I think we're in for
a good chance of another big move.
>> That's
>> Yeah. And it happens towards the end of
the cycles. You know, that was the peak
in for for the real estate cycle 2006.
It had another run, big pullback, and
then went off to the top in in uh that
silver. Same thing for gold.
Where's gold? Yeah, the 19.
There it is. Ran up into 87, pulled
back, and then still had a little bit of
a move in 94, but it's coming off that
hundreds of a percent move, and then
eventually it died out into this low.
So, that was it its own commodity cycle,
and then again, it started to come back.
That was for the new cycle there. So I
guess one one nice thing for the real
estate cycle is once this is over and
commodities have had their run up for
the last 30 years, 25 to 30 years, it
seems unlikely that it's going to just
run again for another 10 to 20 years
with all of the the mounting
narrative that it has to go that high.
You know, we've got that
>> behind the scenes. It's US is
collapsing. Banks around the world are
buying gold to bal, you know, shore up
their balance sheets and all this sort
of stuff. I mean, it's it's done a fair
bit of a move. And if we get this one
last push, I think that could be it for
gold for quite some time, just like
what's happened throughout history, but
we don't want to get off on the on the
negative foot for people when it comes
to to metals just yet.
>> I mean, I I hope gold stays bullish at
least for another year or two. That'd be
nice. But yeah, I mean, maybe talking 10
10 years out or more.
>> Yeah. No, I mean the cycles repeat
themselves, right? I mean, we go through
boom and bust cycles all the time and
gold's no different. Um, and I mean, you
know, this this year has been kind of a
reset year for a lot of markets, right?
Bitcoin, gold, silver, a lot of a lot of
a lot of these. I mean, the only thing
that hasn't really been re one of the
main things that hasn't been resetting
is the stock market, right? the stock
market just kind of just keeps melting
on up to to to new highs after new
highs. But I mean, that's normally what
the stock market does. Um, and it's it's
hard to want to fade it. Uh, even though
we know at some point it probably will
be worth fading. Um,
>> yeah,
>> I mean, we've covered, you know, we've
covered a lot of the different asset
classes, right? We've covered the real
estate cycle. We've covered, let's see,
we've covered metals. um
>> got into stocks, got to the real estate,
what to do with the real estate cycle. I
think it's about
understanding your area if you want to
be a real estate investor
>> and then having a look at the data for
the last at least 10 to 20 years, if you
can get it. If you see in the last five
or so years that your area has been
declining, you might be in for a good
time to start your your journey. doesn't
mean it's going to take go off to the
races next year or in the next two or
three years because we still could still
be going through consolidation and
accumulation. So it takes what we've
seen with real estate, it could be a
decade. So you could be in that time now
where you're getting around the lows
before we start to see things happen in
the early 2030s. So, if it's all brand
new to you, I probably wouldn't wait
till the end because like putting down
contracts and learning about how that
works with financing, it's a bit of a
tough game and it's easier to get
finance when the markets are good
because at the bottom of a real estate
cycle, credit conditions are terrible
and the banks aren't lending and jobs
are usually a little bit hard to come
by, wages aren't increasing. So, it's
just harder to get money at that time.
So, a lot of people will wait till the
end. That's what they say. Well, should
I buy now or should I wait? It's like
you've got to be on the ball. You got to
have your finances in check to get into
that stage. Otherwise, Yeah.
>> Well, I mean, I've looked some into the
real estate market, you know, in terms
of being an investor, but I just I feel
like the math hasn't been that favorable
for the last couple, you know, the last
few years. Like, it just seems like, you
know, everything's expensive. Like
prices are high, interest rates are
high. Like, it's been I I think it's
been hard to justify. I mean, I know you
get a lot of tax breaks with real
estate, and I have a lot of friends that
just like swear by real estate. Like,
that's what they buy. They don't buy
stocks. They don't buy anything. They
just go buy real estate, and they're
they're landlords, you know? Um, but
like when you calculate out some of the
returns from these places, I would
figure I would realize I'm only going to
be getting like a 3 to 4% return uh on
it. And I'm like, gosh, like I like if I
wanted to do that, like I could just put
it in a T bill and and make that uh and
then I don't have to be a landlord, you
know, I don't have to deal with tenants.
Now, again, there are tax breaks that
occur. Uh there's other reasons. I mean,
the the actual price of the house could
also go up, which then makes it more
more worthwhile. But I think that was
one of the things that I was kind of
having a hard time with was I was like,
I'd rather just put it in the stock
market um than than throw it into, you
know, throw it in some real estate
rental property and then have to be a
landlord and and deal with all that to
to probably underperform what I would
have done had I just put it in the stock
market. But again, like I know that line
of thinking eventually doesn't work out,
right? like eventually the stock market,
you know, will go down and and it will
humble people. But again, like I I do
believe to some degree we are a product
of our experiences and, you know, for my
investing career, that's just kind of
how it's, you know, what I've what I've
focused on.
>> Well, I mean, it sounds like you've got
your own strategy and everyone's
different. So, for you, investing in a
stock market makes far more sense. It's
just way less levers to stuff around
with. You just put your money in. It's
like nice and simple. If you want to get
out, it's liquid. You just sell. Real
estate, you can add value to it. So,
even if you're not getting in the stock
market, you have to buy at the price and
that's it. If you get it at the lows,
great. If not, real estate, you can
start to add some value to it. And I'm
sure your mates have talked about that
as well.
>> The the reason why I'm looking at real
estate now is because in some areas in
Australia, they they seem relatively
undervalued. Like they're selling for
less than you can build them for. And
>> okay,
>> I'm looking for another area to put some
cash because I don't want to put it all
into the stock market because then
obviously you got to um you have your
risk adjusted returns. If you start to
see that tank, you're like, well, I'll
have less volatility in my real estate
position. It's obviously a longerterm
outlook. Maybe it's only getting four,
five, six% now, but the the longer term
outlook is that we're expecting capital
growth. So, you're looking for the
capital growth. you've got some yield on
it now and you've just got to be patient
for that position maybe 5 10 15 years
and it has to be those areas that look
undervalued that you've done your
research on. So yeah, it does take a bit
more a bit more work but it's to sort of
balance that portfolio so we're not all
invested in the stock market but you
know each of their own. No no no right
or wrong. Yeah, I mean, as you saw, I
mean, you're it's very localized, right?
In Australia, if prices are down a lot,
it would probably make a lot more sense.
But in my in my area, prices are not
down at all, you know, and they haven't
been down. Um
>> Yeah. I mean, my area, they're not down.
It's so high. I'm not buying in my area.
I'm looking out.
>> Okay. So, you're going out and buying
elsewhere.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Far far away. Areas that
have got a really terrible uh sentiment
at the moment. Mel, you've heard of
Melbourne?
>> Yeah, of course.
>> Yeah. like that area. It's just shot to
crap. Everyone hates it. And the unit
prices are insane. It's It's
>> How's it in Sydney? How's it in Sydney?
>> Um it's Sydney is coming down, but it
hasn't been as bad as Melbourne. So, the
top end's gotten hit pretty hard. Stuff
that's over $3 million in Sydney, 20 25%
in some suburbs. The lower end is
holding okay, and some areas have been
coming down. So, two bed units or
apartments, I think you guys call them
condos there. It's been relatively
stable in some of those markets on the
outer edges of the city because we've
had interest rate rises. People can't
afford the same property that they could
afford previously and that sort of
pushed the buyers to the bottom end. So,
you're starting to see a bit of a
turnaround at the bottom end and a drop
off the top end.
>> Okay. All right.
>> Yeah. I mean, I'm heading to New Zealand
next month. Maybe I should look for some
uh some real estate deals while I'm
there.
>> Have a look at some of the stuff around
Victoria, Melbourne, and this peninsula.
>> It's it's immaculate and it's very
cheap.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Maybe I'll have to get That's the
the one. What are your what one last
question? What what's your view on
REITs? Because I've always like when
I've ever looked into
>> perform very well. I don't have
>> Yeah, that's what I've noticed. They
just underperform the S&P from what I've
seen.
>> Yeah. It's like you're It's like you're
investing in real estate, but you're
you're not you're leaving the upside to
the people that actually manage the
stuff.
>> They take all their percentages off the
top and you're just not getting much
with it.
>> Okay. So, so you would say if you want
to get into real estate, actually get
into it. Don't just half get into it by
buying a REIT.
>> Kind of like buying Bitcoin. You're
better off just buying Bitcoin, holding
it for yourself,
>> right? Yeah. Yeah. That makes sense. I
mean, and and for years, you see people
kind of like lose their way in the in
the crypto industry and and start buying
all sorts of stuff that ends up just
bleeding to Bitcoin in the end. Um,
>> it's kind of crazy. Yeah. I mean, I I
feel like there's there's probably been
a lot of people over the last 5 years in
crypto that became Bitcoin maxis after
just watching everything else eventually
just bleed to Bitcoin. And I mean, I
also think that's sort of like a
maturing thing, too, for a lot of people
is like you get to the point where you
realize there's always going to be a
time where some altcoins are doing well
and and there's, you know, stuff going
on, but then
>> at some point you're just like, you know
what? I just want to put most if not all
of my crypto portfolio just into Bitcoin
and then just like forget about it,
right?
>> Um,
>> exactly. It's
>> Anyway, we could get on a tangent on
Bitcoin as well. I'm just like I don't
know what's happening with that over the
next few years at least. But maybe we'll
save that for another video.
>> I mean the the the rest of this year is
certainly interesting. I mean we've you
know we've had several lows, right? We
had a low in February and I was on your
channel back in I think like May or
something. And I know you were also in
the camp that we were going to go lower.
Um and we did and then now we're
bouncing again. And now there's this big
argument, right, as to whether this is
it or if there's another low. I mean,
frankly, I I do think the right strategy
for Bitcoin is just DCAing it throughout
the second half of the midterm year.
Like that's what's normally worked for
me. And my only regret in 2022, which is
not buying more. Um like I did buy some
>> I did buy some in 2022, but I look back
and I'm like, yeah, like I I could have
bought more, right? And like I that was
one of my biggest regrets in 2023 and
probably one of the biggest mistakes I
made in in the last Bitcoin cycle was
not fully getting on board right away,
right? And it kind of taking a little
bit a little bit longer uh you know to
to to get on board. And I mean it was
one of those things where you know you
you see it happening and and you want to
you want to be right, right? You want to
be right. But I I think that that DCAing
for Bitcoin, especially in that second
half of the midterm year, has has always
worked out. And it's it's really hard to
believe that it won't work out this
time. Um at least in the short term,
right? At least in the short term. And
then we'll have to face the music with
the real estate cycle that you're
talking about as to what does that mean
for the upside, you know, in 2028 or
2029. Like does it get does it get do
you think that Bitcoin could top sooner
than it normally does? Like normally it
tops in you know Q4 of the post having
year. Do you think it
>> this time? I think I think this will be
a left hand left translated cycle. You
know the left hand you got your
>> Yeah. Left translated. Yeahur like the
first in the first two years or
something.
>> Yes. Yeah. Okay.
>> I think I think that's going to be the
case. If we got 2026 that'll be max like
20 28. I think there's going to be some
sort of catalyst 28 29 for global things
and that's that sends it all all down.
Another a big cycle that I've watched is
a have you heard of the Schmita cycle
the sevenyear cycle? I
>> have not.
>> It's it's from the Jewish I think um the
Jewish Bible or Yeah. from from that
those years. But every seven years is
like a a reset year. It's like a a year
that's down. And when you look back over
I don't know hundred years it's like
every seven years starting
>> was the next one 2028 or 2029
>> 2029 2022 was the last one 2015 didn't
go anywhere 2008 2001 1994 was basically
flat coming off a low 1987 1980 you know
it's just
>> right I mean 1980 was yeah we dropped
what like 20 to 30% in the stock market
87 was brutal I mean 87 was like yeah it
was like 35% practically overnight.
>> The year still finished up, but yeah,
over
>> but 94 was just sideways, right? Like 94
wasn't a bad year
>> because I mean that was actually one of
the years sort of leading into the stock
the the dot bubble.
>> Um
>> yeah.
>> Yeah, I can see that
>> for a bull market to hold flat.
>> That's the way I look at it. I read you
using the read of the seven years,
>> right?
>> 2015
>> in some ways, you know, in some ways we
already had a left translated cycle. If
you look at Bitcoin valued against other
currencies or maybe not other currencies
but I mean against the US dollar Bitcoin
tops when it always tops but against
gold actually it topped in 2024. So you
almost have to wonder was that kind of a
warning sign of you know what might
happen in the next cycle as well. Maybe
it'll be left translated against gold
again. Um because it was already it
already happened once and so we already
it already proved that it can do it. So
we should be openminded to it happening
again. That's what we saw is against
gold it topped earlier, silver topped
earlier, stock markets, it topped
earlier, and we just saw more of that
credit just leaving Bitcoin, the
liquidity leaving Bitcoin earlier,
>> right? Did I think it even topped
against some of the like did it top
against the euro earlier? I mean, I know
it topped against the US dollar in in
October, but I feel like I I it might
not have been the euro, but I think
there were some fiat currencies where it
actually topped sooner than than October
because remember, I mean, the dollar was
really weak at the time. And I think
some other currencies were slightly
stronger, I believe, than the dollar.
>> We could settle it with looking at a
chart, but then we have to bring that
up.
>> Yeah, that's fine. I I I just I I I do
think there's evidence, right? Like I I
think you could be right about it being
left translated, but
we take it what one quarter at a time
and and not get too far ahead of
ourselves because who knows, right? Who
knows what'll happen? But
>> well, every time I think about that and
do that, it just stops me from making a
trade because I'm like, "Oh, if it
doesn't long,
>> if it's not going to be that long,
what's the point?" So, I just got to
look at the riskreward. If it's at this
level, is it worth the upside for me? If
not, just wait. Look
>> I try to remind myself, trade the market
you have, not the market you want,
right? just trade what you have and stop
worrying about the mark getting the
exact market that you want. Um
>> yeah, so many more simple things like
that you can do. Well, it's not not too
complicated.
>> Well, that's the thing, too. Like, if
Bitcoin bottoms, let's say it bottoms at
57K or if it goes a little bit lower,
whatever, whatever the range is. I mean,
if it goes back up to 100K, like that's
still a decent return. Um, if it goes to
150, right, that's still a great return.
It's just not great compared to what
people are wanting.
But it would be outperform, it would be
more than likely outperforming what the
stock market would be doing during that
same period of time would be my guess,
right? And like if Bitcoin can go up one
or 200% in the next bull market at
least. I mean, the stock market, I'm not
saying it can't go up that much, but
normally Bitcoin outperforms the stock
market uh you know, during during those
years. So I I think you know some people
just need to adjust their expectations
as well. Um instead of you know stop
going for these like thousandx gains and
micro caps and and be okay with you know
smaller returns and something 50%. You
know if it does 100% you're never going
to catch the 100%. So I just look at it
like what what could I catch in the
middle and then is that worth the time?
Is it worth the risk? Am I going to put
enough into it to make it worth the
while? Because, you know, you're
probably going to put more into a stock
portfolio than you are into Bitcoin for
this stage of the cycle, for this stage
of the trade. Is it really worth it? And
when I do those numbers up, like
sometimes it is, sometimes it isn't. And
I just share that with, you know,
>> members or or YouTube or whatever. It's
just
>> some people that's all they like it's
all their money and all they want to do
is put it into Bitcoin. Like in that
case, you're probably going to get
bigger returns from Bitcoin than stock
market in a particular window,
>> right?
>> But do you have that time,
>> right? It's like if you bought Bitcoin
at 126K in October, you it's going to be
a lot harder to outperform the stock
market. But if you're buying it in, you
know, August 2026, you probably have a
better chance over the next year. Um,
yeah, I mean that's a great point, but I
mean, you know, timing the market is
really hard as many people have learned
and I have learned many, many times,
right? It is, it is really difficult and
that's why the best investors will tell
you not to. Um,
>> talk about it day in day out. It's just
>> I know. No, I mean it's true. Like I I
literally just I buy index funds every
single month, right? every month on a
Monday, like the first Monday of the
month, I just go buy them even if I
think we're going to have a correction
because I'm like there because there's
been so many times where like we will
have a correction um and I feel like a
genius, but then there's other times
where we don't have a correction, I'm
just like I should have just bought
anyways, you know? Um so
>> did you ever look at it like pricing it
up with all of the the stuff that you do
and just go look if it goes down
>> 8% buy more? So you have sort of like a
pyramid strategy.
>> Yeah. So basically like I buy monthly
and then I try to figure out like when
it might correct so that then I can add
more to it. Like I'm not ever selling
stocks. Um I couldn't even tell you the
la last time I sold an index fund was
probably in uh the the very very
beginning of 20 or was probably in 2021
because I bought you know we bought a
house back then. Um and I you know I
needed to like liquidate some of what we
had so we could just you know have money
to put down on the house. Um, so yeah,
like that was probably the last time I
even sold an index fund. I mean I it's
really I mean the thing is is like when
I sell them like what am I selling them
for? Like what am I going to go put it
in? And usually I don't like a lot of
times I can't like there's nothing else
that I'm looking to really put it in.
Like the the money I have in index funds
is in index funds for a reason. Uh the
money I have in Bitcoin is in Bitcoin
for a reason. you know, like if I'm
selling stocks, I'm usually not I I I
feel like I'd have to be really
convinced that it's truly the, you know,
it's truly over for years. And I don't
know if I would ever get to that point,
you know, before I don't know if I
would. Um I don't know.
>> I mean, like you said, even with
whatever you have, if it fell 60% like
the max that it's done in the last 100
years besides 1929,
>> you just it's going to bounce back
probably. give it five years
>> and then [laughter] it's still sitting
there for whenever you need it.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think that's kind of a
maybe a reason to just have some cash on
hand, especially if you think it's going
to happen, but that doesn't mean be 100%
cash. Um
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> So,
>> yeah.
>> Well, like we've been going for what,
probably an hour now, so maybe we should
go ahead and wrap it up. Um,
>> yeah,
>> guys, if you're not if you're not
subscribed to Jason, again, I will put
the links to his website and his YouTube
channel and whatever socials uh down in
the description below. So, make sure you
guys check that out. And again, if you
want to meet him uh see him in person,
he'll be at the ITC conference uh in
Miami in November. Jason, any any final
thoughts?
>> No, I think that sums it up pretty well.
Maybe we'll come back in a few months,
see what's going on. Otherwise, we'll
we'll chat in November, finally meet
face to face. I'll be my my brain will
be switched from night to morning,
morning to night, and we'll try and make
sense of it.
>> Sounds good. All right. Well, I'll see
see you then. And and again, everyone,
go check out Jason's channel. Definitely
a good follow in the space.
>> Thanks, guys. See you later.